Hello and welcome back to another video
with ItsDrDan, and today we're going to be
going into drawing cis and trans alkenes.
Now one of the things that's really common
to be asked of you by your professors
is to draw structures in different ways.
Mainly it's through expanded or complete
structures, condensed structures
or formulas, and line structures,
whether they're called geometric,
skeletal, there's many different names.
Now, when you're doing it for alkenes,
it's kind of similar to drawing
cyclic structures where you need to
actually show the different shapes
of these bonds, especially when
you have cis or trans capabilities.
You want to make sure you
label your molecules correctly.
Now, what makes alkene so special
is the double bond is considered
to be rigid, meaning that you can't
just rotate it however you want.
It's kind of stuck in its exact structure.
So when we're drawing these,
it's important that we
show the bond connectivity.
as well as that 3D visualization
when we're drawing these.
So if I already asked you a question
of how to draw these, and then
we'll go through this obviously as
an example, is how would you draw
three trans hexene As expanded,
condensed, and as a line structure.
So how do you go through it?
Well, the first thing is when it
comes to expanded, it's when you're
drawing all the bonds, you're drawing
even all your hydrogens, and it tends
to be quite a little bit of a mess.
The biggest thing is when you're
trying to actually showcase these as
cis and trans, is you need to give
indications that you actually have
that trans capability in a structure.
So what I like to do personally, so
with starting with expanded, is I
start from the double bond and then
I draw my weight outwards from it.
And I do the same thing with condensed.
So for example, if I were to write
this, right, I have my double bond and
being that it's at three transhexene,
I'm going to number my double bond
as three and four for the carbons,
because remember when we're numbering,
the first number is shown in the name.
Now what we're going to do is we're
going to build this molecule outwards.
So typically when we're drawing this,
we actually end up showing some of
that three dimensional shape to it.
It doesn't entirely showcase
only the 90 degree that you're
kind of used to with these.
We need to actually show like the angles
to kind of give it the appropriate look.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to
first start by drawing in all my carbons.
So we have carbon number
five and number six.
And then I'm going to put in
carbon number two and number one.
Now what we'll do from there is
we're going to fill in all of our
hydrogens, so keeping our counts.
Um, here I'll put the numbers in so we can
prove to you that we still have a hexene.
Notice that the carbons are moving in
opposite directions too, so we still have
that kind of that trans look to it that
I'm trying to highlight here in yellow,
which I think I'll change to red, just to
kind of help that contrast a little bit.
Okay.
Now what we're going to do is we're
going to fill our hydrogens in.
So the first one, right,
we need to make four bonds.
So we got to have three hydrogens.
On the second one, we're going
to be the same kind of idea.
We're going to try to keep that
90 degrees the best that we can.
Um, even though it looks going
to look a little bit funny here.
So we'll have one hydrogen, two hydrogens.
On the next one, we have
one hydrogen, one hydrogen.
And notice that I kind of put them
pointing in opposite directions to help
illustrate that trans a little bit more.
If you want to do them
as diagonals, you can.
I just, I think that's completely fine.
Um, it doesn't have to be perfect
when it comes to drawing every single
one of these, because it's not the
idea of it to show, uh, perfect
geometry when it comes expanded.
It's just to help us illustrate,
do we have that expanded look?
Now, is this the only way you can do this?
If you want to stick to, let's say, pure
90 degrees, you can do that as well.
The one thing that I, also another way
of doing, one way that I learned, is
if you want to show trans, the whole
idea is you want to try to put the
different groups in opposite directions.
So like, I'll have one hydrogen pointing
up, I'll have the other one pointing down.
And being that those are opposite
of each other, I can then continue
my branch as well, just like this.
This is another option, which I think
is really good, because then you can
actually draw everything as straight.
So these are both acceptable
ways to do expanded structures.
The most important thing is
that you're showing ways to
show that trans capability.
So notice that I have my hydrogens
on opposite sides, so both of
these are acceptable ways to do it.
It kind of just depends
on which one you prefer.
So, now with condensed, the
whole idea here is, is we're
trying to simplify our structure.
So let's look at that and how to do that.
My button on every single carbon.
So I do the same thing.
I start at my double bond.
I write my CHs in there.
Now, when you are doing this, the
most important thing is we do want
to try to show that trans capability.
So you could just write CHs.
But personally, this
is where I like to, um,
So now we're going to be showing
our condensed structures.
What I personally like to do is
I like to do the same strategy.
I like to start from the double bond.
And what we're going to be doing
is we're actually going to be doing
some three dimensional shape here.
So I have one hydrogen pointing up and
one pointing down, and then I'm going
to do my two carbons on each side.
So when we have this trans structure,
You're going to write CH2CH3 being
that we're minimizing each of these
different carbon areas that we have over
here, bringing in all those hydrogens.
And we're going to do the same
thing up here, um, as well.
And notice I didn't draw it
pointing up and down the exact
same way like I did the other one.
That's okay, it does not have
to be the same way, because if I
were to rotate this molecule, they
would be the exact same thing.
So this is how you can
do a condensed structure.
Now when it comes to trying to draw a
skeletal, we're going to be, I like to
do where I started the double bond again.
I think it makes it a little bit easier
because you're trying to make sure
that you show how many carbons there
are, and that you have the correct
geometry in your structure as well.
So if you kind of look here, I have that
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, And I still have that,
that trans type of structure where they're
both pointing up and down in my molecule.
Okay, which is kind of the
ultimate idea, see how they're
both opposite of each other.
Which is that most important part when
we're trying to illustrate cis and trans.
So this would be how to draw
skeletal, and you need to show
that in all your structures.
If it was cis, let's say, instead, you
would all, which we're going to do in the
next one, you need to just make sure that
you have that U shape in your structure.
Let's go on to our next
example and take a look.
Okay, so for this example, we're
going to draw cis 5 t butyl 2
octene as an expanded, condensed,
and also as a line structure.
So this one is a harder example that
I thought would be good to pick,
being that I feel like a lot of
tutorials and And the textbook examples
always go over really easy ones.
So with this one, what we're going
to do is, I like to personally
start with the double bond itself.
Now when it comes to expanded,
the entire idea here is we're
trying to show all of the bonds.
So everything that's possible.
And the thing was with this one as well,
it's also a really big thing that you
try to use 90 degree angles as much as
possible, it's supposed to represent
a Lewis structure is the entire idea.
So I start with the double bond, which
was number two is where that bond starts.
And what we're going to do is we're
going to fill in the rest of the chain.
Now being that it is cis, what
we're going to see is here is it's
easier if you emphasize carbon
bonds going in the same direction.
So see how they're both going
horizontal, this is an option to do cis.
It can also go together vertically
as well, which is another choice.
Right, so you're going to see that
I have my, my carbons going together
sideways, and then notice that I'm
putting my hydrogens together as well.
So this is helping us show that CIS
characteristic, right, and that's kind
of the goal with this is you need to
try to show it, um, even though this
is not the most common way to draw
these kinds of structures, um, with
expanded, it's more to help you be
able to visualize all those bonds.
Okay.
So we're going to fill
in our carbons, right?
We're going to count all of our
bonds, and then we're going to
connect it to each individual carbon.
So one of the easy ways to do this is draw
your carbon chain first, and then we're
going to fill in all those hydrogens.
Now keep in mind, we do have a
special branch at number five, which
is one of, it's a t butyl branch.
And if you're not sure exactly
about those, you can refer to
my video on different types of
butyl and propyl branches, which
will help go over that as well.
But on number five we
have this butyl group.
So what you can do is you can
actually draw like an awkwardly
long carbon bond so that it gives
you room to expand the structure.
So we're going to start with the carbon,
right, and being this is four carbons,
we're going to draw three lines all
around this with a carbon at each one.
And then you can see in yellow
all four carbons that are here.
Now what we'll do is next
we'll fill in our hydrogens.
So we'll have three hydrogens
on each one of these.
Little methyl attachments in the t butyl.
So you can see we have our complete
structure here and it's every little
detail that we can do, and this is
not the only way you can do expanded.
There's other options too.
It's kind of all about your
interpretation of how to show it
and what's accepted in your class.
But this is one way to do it.
Now, the next part with condensed, this
is when you start getting a little easier.
Um, being that now you can actually
sort of show some of those three
dimensional characteristics.
So let's say I start once
again on the double bond.
What you can do is now is you can
actually use some diagonal lines.
So I have my CH3 from carbon number one.
I'm going to point it upwards
to show that U bowl shape.
So we have number one, number
two, number three, and then
we'll have number four coming up.
So we can see that, okay,
well, here's our CH2.
And we have that bowl shape.
So I'm going to highlight that in green
just so you can kind of see that U
shape that, that is, that's here, right?
That's going to be the cis part.
So that's exactly what we want.
Now we're going to continue that.
So we're going to go to the next
one, which is carbon number five.
We have carbon six and
seven, which will condense.
Um, so let's kind of
label those for ourselves.
And now with our t butyl, this
is where it kind of is up to
you, how you want to do it.
Personally, I like doing a little
line to have it come above.
You can also put it in
parentheses as well.
So it's going to be one carbon
with a CH3, you're gonna have
three CH3s coming all around it.
And that's what we saw in
this structure up here, right?
You see like this, this like fan
kind of type shape here, that where
it's all coming around that carbon.
And that's how we can condense it down.
With that, that's going to move on
to skeletal, which is even easier,
or geometric, line bond, line
angle, all those different names.
And what we're going to do is
we're just going to draw each line.
Remember, every corner represents carbons.
So we're going to put that double bond in.
Now we're going to start
showing the zigzag.
So we have carbon 4, 5,
and then we do 7 and 8.
And so being that on carbon number
5, it's currently going downwards.
So what we're going to do is we're
going to point our t butyl downwards.
And um, just to kind of answer the
questions, like maybe if we're expanded
and condensed, It doesn't matter if
you have a pointing downwards or not
in expanding condensed or upwards.
It's up to you how you want to do it.
Um, but this one generally, if a
pretty big rule of thumb when it comes
to these structures, if you see the
geometric pointing down like this, right?
Or I have it in like that.
All right.
It's actually really
like blue highlighting.
Let's open this red highlighting here.
So it's already pointing down.
So what we want to do is we want to also
have the branch pointing in the same
direction, which is the thought here.
Okay, let's go take a
look at our next example.
Okay, so for this one, I said, let's
draw one ethyl, two methyl, cyclohexene
as condensed and as line structure.
So I see a lot of students always
are asking me and how, how do
you draw cyclic structures?
Um, just being that it is
really very, very different.
Um, so the first thing is, is for this one
is let's draw the ring structure first.
So with condensed, what we have to make
sure we do is just like double bonds
is we need to show the connectivity.
So what I'm going to do is I'm
going to draw kind of connecting
all these little double bonds here.
So we're going to start the
double bond is always going
to be number one in this case.
So when we have this guy, we're
gonna kind of fill that in.
Now we have an Ethel and a methyl
connected to our double bond.
So Ethel is at the first
spot, methyl iss at the other.
So what I'm gonna draw here is I'm
gonna make a little line for us this
show where one of these is gonna go,
and then where the other branches.
Now I'm gonna finish kind of making
my ring structure first, so I
just wanna put most of the carbons
in just to kind of help, help
illustrate this as much as possible.
So it's six members.
So we're going to put all those in.
So just like so.
And I know it's not the most perfect
ring structure, but that's okay.
Now, what we're going to do now is
we're going to fill in any more carbons.
So the only one that's missing
is part of our ethyl group.
So what we'll have here is we have our CH2
and CH3 and then our CH3 for our methyl.
All right.
So with this structure,
I have all my numbers in.
So that way we can kind of
see where everything is.
We see we have our double bond, we
have our ethyl, we have our methyl,
and what we're now going to do is just
make sure we have all of our bonds.
So we can see that for this carbon number
one, we have one, two, three, four.
We're good there.
Carbon number two, we have
one, two, three, four.
So that means that they are fine.
So what we will now do is write in
our CH2s for each of our other, uh,
carbons that are around our ring.
And this is how you draw a condensed
structure for a ring with groups.
And we have a double bond.
Now, can you have cis or
trans in ring structures?
You actually can.
It depends on kind of how it's drawn.
Most of them tend to be cis, if there
is, if it is actually drawn in there
because it is wrapping on itself.
But if you have like a very, very big
ring, like maybe 10 to 12 carbons,
it is possible to have trans as well.
One of the biggest examples like
a dodecane, uh, dodecane has
a cis and trans capabilities.
So it is possible.
Um, this case would not have either.
Uh, so this one is neither cis nor trans.
Now, when you're doing the actual line
structure, it is a lot easier to do it.
So what we're going to do is
we're going to draw our six
member ring the best that we can.
And then what we'll do is we'll
put our double bond and then our,
and then our ethyl and our methyl.
And I know this isn't the
most perfect, uh, structure.
And just to kind of illustrate that it
doesn't always have to be at the top here,
um, I put it on the side just to kind of
illustrate, hey, it can be somewhere else.
It's up to you as the person drawing
this, where it's going to go.
And then we can put our ethyl
and our methyl in our structure.
So just to show that I kind of turn
this, so this is one, two, three, four.
five.
So you can draw in different locations.
It's up to you.
You can draw the top, side, middle,
bottom, whatever you like, um, as long as
you are numbering everything correctly.
And that's how you do condense.
You can do this as expanded,
but it's a little annoying to
do in terms of ring structures.
You've got to blow up all of
your different, uh, bonds,
just like you do before.
Typically when it comes to the point
you're getting an alkenes, you kind
of stop doing that kind of thing.
All right.
So this has been how to draw all
the different alkene structures.
As you can see, it can get a little
bit more complicated and it can be a
lot of work, depending on kind of what
your thought processes, it might be
easier to start a skeletal and then work
backwards to the more expanded ones.
Some people like starting as condensed and
then go on to the expanded end to line.
That's okay.
It just depends on how does your brain
think through actually all these bonds?
How can you write them?
Do what's easiest for you to remember them
and keep practicing is the ultimate thing.
Okay.
I hope that this video helped.
Thank you so much for listening, and
I hope to see you all in the future.
All right, bye now.